P+34 659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

# FLLIS PhD Student in ML

**Personal WWW** Google Scholar GitHub & LinkedIn

Me – I am a PhD Student at ELLIS Alicante with a strong interest in Algorithmic Fairness using Causality and Graph theory supervised by Nuria Oliver (ELLIS) and Manuel Gomez Rodriguez (MPI-SWS). ELLIS is an AI research network focused on excellence, with 35 units in 15 countries of Europe. ELLIS has 200 PhD students around Europe with an acceptance rate of <5%.

Research Topic – My current thesis addresses concepts such as transparency, reliability, and fairness in Machine Learning, which urgently need to be taken into account in critical decision-making ML scenarios. We also delve in the decision making in Graph Neural Networls. In my thesis, (1) we study what data might be the cause of unfairness or what data should look like in a "fair" world (2) fairness in graph data to capture complex data relationships and human-generated data, and (3) study effective deployment of AI in the real world on human-AI collaboration scenarios. Specifically, we first study the influence of each data point in a fairness metric for reducing the bias in ML models using Data Valuation. Second, we study Graph Rewiring methods that ensure fair graph data, and finally, we use *Human-in-the-loop* methods to theoretically improve the human-AI teaming on specific tasks. Last but not least, we study the intersection of AI and Law for a really effective societal adoption of Al. In sum, what data causes unfairness, what data should look in a fair world, it's efficient implementation in the real world and their societal effects.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD Student / Fairness in ML

Dec 2021 - Present

ELLIS Alicante – (European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems) – Max Planck Institute

- Researching on Fairness in ML decision making leveraging graph theory, game theory and causality.
- Supervised by Dr. Nuria Oliver (ELLIS) and Dr. Manuel Gómez Rodríguez (MPI-SWS, Germany).
- 6-months exchange at Max Plank Institute for Software Systems (MPI-SWS), Germany, Feb-Aug, 2024.
- Funded by RESUMAIS (Intel), ELIAS (European Project [101120237-HORIZON-CL4-2022-HUMAN-02]), Bank Sabadell and GVA.
- More info: [European Lab. for Learning and Intelligent Systems ELLIS] [Research Topic]

# **MSc in AI & Data Science**

Jan 2020 — Jan 2021

GPA:9.7/10

Universitat Oberta de Catalunya

- Evaluated both Masters and Thesis with Honors
- Thesis supervised by Dr. Baris Kanber from University Collegue of London: Deep CAE for denoising T1 brain MRI

# **BSc in Computer Engeneering**

Sep 2015 — Jun 2019

GPA:8.9/10

- University of Burgos
- Evaluated both Bachelors and Thesis with Honors • Extraordinary award: best student in the promotion.
- Thesis carried out in ADMIRABLE research lab: Use of biomarkers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson
- Press coverage: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

**Research Staff** Jan 2020 — Aug 2021 University of Burgos, Spain

ADMIRABLE and DATAHES research labs

- European project [2019-1-ES01-KA204-065615] Self-Regulated Learning: SmartArt.
- Behavioural VR data analysis and Platform UBUMLaas
- Academic production shown in Publications section (Topic: Network Science and Web mining)

**AI Consultant** *Aug 2019 — Jan 2020* Ernst & Young Madrid, Spain

• Building ML models for RPA integration: Intelligent Automation

Dec 2018 — Jun 2019 Research intern ADMIRABLE research lab University of Burgos, Spain

• Research intern with collaboration scholarship. Research in the project Use of biomarkers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson (BSc Thesis).

P+34 659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

# **ELLIS PhD Student in ML**

Personal WWW Google Scholar GitHub & LinkedIn

### **PRE PRINTS**

- [1] Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez and Julio Losada. "The Impact of AI in Business: Exploring Legal Implications of Causality in Algorithmic Decision Making, a Spanish Laboral Law Use Case". Submitted. 2024.
- [2] Kajetan Schweighofer, **Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez**, Sepp Hochreiter, and Nuria Oliver. "The Disparate Benefits of Deep Ensembles". Submitted. 2024.

#### CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS AND TUTORIALS

- [1] Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez and Ameya Velingker. "Tutorial on Graph Learning: Principles, Challenges, and Open Directions". In: Proceedings of the 41st International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2024). Tutorial. Vienna, Austria, July 2024. URL: https://icml.cc/virtual/2024/tutorial/35233.
- [2] Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez, Georgina Curto, and Nuria Oliver. "Structural Group Unfairness: Measurement and Mitigation by means of the Effective Resistance". In: WWW 2024 2nd Workshop on Trustworthy Learning on Graphs (TrustLOG). 2024. URL: https://arxiv.org/pdf/2305.03223.pdf.
- [3] Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez and Nuria Oliver. "Towards Algorithmic Fairness by means of Instance-level Data Re-weighting based on Shapley Values". In: ICLR 2024 Workshop on Data-centric Machine Learning Research (DMLR). 2024. URL: https://openreview.net/forum?id=ivf1QaxEGQ.
- [4] Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez, Francisco Escolano, Nuria Oliver, and Edwin Hancock. "Tutorial on Graph Rewiring: From Theory to Applications in Fairness". In: Proceedings of the Learning on Graphs Conference (LoG 2022). Tutorial. Virtual Event, Dec. 2022. URL: https://ellisalicante.org/tutorials/GraphRewiring.
- [5] Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, Ahmed Begga, Francisco Escolano, and Nuria Oliver. "DiffWire: Inductive Graph Rewiring via the Lovász Bound". In: *The First Learning on Graphs Conference*. 2022. URL: https://openreview.net/forum?id=IXvfIex0mX6f.
- [6] Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, José Luis Garrido-Labrador, and Alicia Olivares-Gil. "Computer Science doctoral research in Spain. A relational perspective". In: *Actas de la XIX Conferencia de la Asociación Española para la Inteligencia Artificial*. Universidad de Málaga. Málaga, 2021, pp. 667–672. ISBN: 978-84-09-30514-8. URL: https://caepia20-21.uma.es/inicio\_files/caepia20-21-actas.pdf#page702.
- [7] José Luis Garrido-Labrador, José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, Virginia Ahedo, Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, César García-Osorio, José Ignacio Santos, and José Manuel Galán. "Network analysis of co-participation in thesis examination committees in an academic field in Spain". In: Abstract book of the 14th International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Industrial Management and XXIV Congreso de Ingeniería de Organización. Universidad Carlos III de Madrid. Burgos, 2020. URL: https://eventos.uc3m.es/\_files/\_event/\_43190/\_editorFiles/file/BookOfAbstracts10.pdf.

# **JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS**

- [1] José Luis Garrido-Labrador, José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, Virginia Ahedo, **Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez**, César García-Osorio, José Ignacio Santos, and José Manuel Galán. "Análisis de la red de co-participaciones en tribunales de tesis de un área científica en España". In: *Dirección y Organización* 79 (2023), pp. 59–67. DOI: 10.37610/dyo.v0i79.638.
- [2] Alicia Olivares Gil, Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez, José Miguel Ramírez Sanz, José Luis Garrido Labrador, Virginia Ahedo García, César García Osorio, José Ignacio Santos Martín, José Manuel Galán Ordax, et al. "Mapping the scientific structure of organization and management of enterprises using complex networks". In: International Journal of Production Management and Engineering 10.1 (2022), pp. 65–76. URL: https://polipapers.upv.es/index.php/IJPME/article/view/16666.
- [3] Esther Cubo, Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez, Álvar Arnaiz-González, José Francisco Díez-Pastor, Meredith Spindler, Adriana Cardozo, Alvaro Garcia-Bustillo, Zoltan Mari, and Bastiaan R Bloem. "Videoconferencing Software Options for Telemedicine: A Review for Movement Disorder Neurologists". In: Frontiers in neurology (2021), p. 1812. URL: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fneur.2021.745917/full.

P+34 659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

# **ELLIS PhD Student in ML**

**Personal WWW** Google Scholar GitHub & LinkedIn

María Consuelo Sáiz-Manzanares, Ismael Ramos Pérez, Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, Sandra Rodríguez Arribas, Leandro Almeida, and Caroline Françoise Martin. "Analysis of the learning process through eye tracking technology and feature selection techniques". In: Applied Sciences 11.13 (2021), p. 6157. URL: https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/11/13/6157/htm.

#### **HONORS & AWARDS**

## Selected for London Geometry and Machine Learning Summer School[Link]

Imperial College London, July 2024

Selected to participate with Joshua Robinson.

Heidelberg Laureate Forum Young Researcher [Link]

Heidelberg Laureate Forum Foundation, Sep 2023

Selected among 200 young researchers from around the world to participate in the 10th HLFF a highly competitive and prestigious platform, where a few students get the opportunity to interact with Turing Award winners, Abel Prize winners, and Fields Medalists.

Top 10% Reviewer AISTATS 2023 [Link]

International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics, April 2023

Selected in the top 10% best reviewers in AISTATS 2023 Conference.

Top 10% Reviewer ICML 2022 [Link]

International Conference on Machine Learning, July 2022

Selected in the top 10% best reviewers in ICML 2022 Conference. FPU PhD Fellowship (Declined) - FPU20/03687

Spanish Government - Ministry of Universities, Sep 2021

Grants for pre-doctoral contracts in Spanish Universities.

Extraordinary Award of Bachelors in Computer Engineering

Council of the University of Burgos, Dec 2019

Top 1 student the Degree in Computer Engineering of the University of Burgos.

Prototype Award [Press coverage: 1, 2, 3]

OTRI (Service for Technology Transfer University of Burgos), Feb 2019

Project awarded: Use of bio-markers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson.

**Undergraduated Research Fellowship** 

University of Burgos, Dec 2018

Assistant research Fellowship in the Civil Engineering department of the University of Burgos, research group ADMIRABLE

**Courses with honors** 

Bachelor's and Master's

8 out of 10 MSc courses evaluated with honours, included Thesis.

10 BSc courses evaluated with honours, included Thesis.

#### **TALKS**

[Lecture @ DelveDeepLarning] Graph Neural Networks	[Link] Online, Sep 2024
[Tutorial @ ICML] Graph Learning: Principles, Challenges, and Open Directions	[Link] Vienna, Jul 2024
→ w/ A. Velingker (Google Research). Panelists: M. Bronstein (Oxford, DeepMind), M. Galkin (Intel), B. Perozzi (Google), C. Morris (Aachen Univ.)	
[TurstLoG wk@www.conference] Structural Group Unfairness in Social Networks	[Link] Singapore, May 2024
[Guest Lecture @ Univeristy of Notre Dame] Polarization in Networks and Social Capital	[Link] Indiana , USA, Feb 2024
[Algorithmic Societies ERC @ CCCB] Algorithmic Discrimination	[Link] Barcelona, Nov 2023
[Chamber of Commerce] Round table about Sustainable AI	[Link] Alicante, Jun 2023
[ELLIS-DMMLab (CMU) Workshop] Technical challenges of Algorithmic Fairness	[Link] Alicante, Mar 2023
[European Parliament Committee on Legal Affairs (JURI)] Algorithmic Fairness for EU Parlamentarians	[Link] Alicante, Feb 2023
[Tutorial @ LoG Conference] Graph Rewiring: From Theory to Applications in Fairness	[Link] Online, Dec 2022
[SpainAI] Fairness in AI from Classic Approaches to Data Valuation and Social Networks	[Link] Burgos (Spain), Dec 2022
[PERTE New economy of Language] Discrimination in Al and diversity [L1,L2,L3] Minist	try of Economy (Spain), Oct 2022
[University of Burgos] Fairness in algorithmic decision-making [L1, L2] <i>Univer</i>	sity of Burgos (online), Mar 2022
[ELLIS HCML Reading group] ELLIS + Qualcomm AI Research: GNN and HCML	[Link] Virtual, Feb 2022
- Moderator and Panel Participant	

- Panel: Pim de Haan, Carlos Castillo, Efstatios Gavves and Manuel Gómez Rodríguez

[ELLIS Talks] Fairness in Machine Learning: From introduction to current approaches [Link] University of Alicante, Jan 2022 Data processing in Advance Learning Technology [Link] Self-Regulated Learning in SmartArt Learning conference, Jul 2021

## SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY SERVICES

## - Chair member

[Co-Organizer]  $3^{rd}$  LoG Conference 2024 [Associate Chair] ICML 2024 Associate Chair

Virtual, Dec 2024 Viena, Jul 2024

P+34 659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

# FLLIS PhD Student in MI

Personal WWW Google Scholar GitHub & LinkedIn

Vienna, Jul 2022

Online, Dec 2022

Alicante, Sep 2022

bi-weekly sessions

[Co-Organizer] Tutorial on ICML 2024: "Graph Learning: Principles, Challenges, and Open Directions"

[Co-Organizer] Tutorial on LoG 2022 Conference: "Graph Rewiring: From Theory to Applications in Fairness"

[Co-Organizer] ELLIS Doctoral Symposium 2022

022

[Co-Organizer] ELLIS HCML Reading Group: guest sessions and round tables

## Program Committee member

NeurIPS 2024 - Thirty-eighth Annual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems

NeurIPS 2024 - Workshop "Algorithmic Fairness through the Lens of Metrics and Evaluation"

IC2S2 2024 - International Conference on Computational Social Sciences

FAccT 2023 - ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (ACM FAccT)

AISTATS 2024 - Artificial Intelligence and Statistics 2024

NeurIPS 2023 - Workshop "Algorithmic Fairness Through the Lens of Time"

AISTATS 2023 - Artificial Intelligence and Statistics 2023 - Top 10% Outstanding Reviewer

NeurIPS 2022 - Workshop "Algorithmic Fairness through the Lens of Causality and Privacy"

ICML 2022 - International Conference on Machine Learning - Top 10% Outstanding Reviewer

NeurIPS 2022 - Workshop "Human Centered AI"

ECML-PKDD 2022 - European Conference on ML and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases

WWW 2022 - The Web Conference 2022, ACM, New York.

#### - Journal Reviewer

PeerJ 2023 - PeerJ Computer Science 2023

TNNLS 2023/24 - IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems 2023/24 - Graph Special Issue

JMLR 2023 - Journal of Machine Learning Research

Journal of Complexity 2022.

TCSS'22 - IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems 2022.

### - More

Organizer and moderator of Qualcomm+ELLIS Reading Group Session about GNN+HCML

→ Round table: Pim de Haan, Carlos Castillo, Efstatios Gavves and Manuel Gómez Rodríguez

Volunteer at NeurIPS Workshop "Human-Centered AI"

Online, Feb 2022

Virtual, Dec 2021

## - Open Source software

Open source code from all academic projects, an also both BSc and MSc final projects on GH Main contributor of *Lightly version 1.1.2* in Lightly AI PyTorch-based library for Self-Supervised Learing. More open source codes in GitHub: applications, experiments and data analysis

## SKILLS

Languages and libs More interests Communication Python, R, Java, Tensorflow, PyTorch, PyGeometric, NetworkX

Mathematical optimization, Mathematical Modeling, GNNs, Causality, Online Learning

Spanish (native), English (Fluent)

For pictures, and more information, please refer to my webpage.

**Updated September 2024**